<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The coppie of a letter sent into England by a gentleman, from the towne of Saint Denis in France Wherein is truely set forth the good successe of the Kings Maiesties forces against the Leaguers and the Prince of Parmas power. With the taking of a conuoie of victuals sent by the enemie to succour Paris. And the grieuous estate of the said citie at this present.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118410</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853617</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853617</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00009)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 422:03, 1553:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The coppie of a letter sent into England by a gentleman, from the towne of Saint Denis in France Wherein is truely set forth the good successe of the Kings Maiesties forces against the Leaguers and the Prince of Parmas power. With the taking of a conuoie of victuals sent by the enemie to succour Paris. And the grieuous estate of the said citie at this present.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12, 15-23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Scarlet for Thomas Nelson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>2nd part, "A treatise concerning the extreme famine of the citie of Paris at this present" has caption title on B3r.</note>
                  <note>Pages 13, 14 are missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>2nd part formerly also STC 19199.</note>
                  <note>2nd part identified as STC 19199 on UMI microfilm, reel 1553.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (parts 1 and 2) and in the Bodleian Library (part 2 only).</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 422 (British Library copy, parts 1 and 2) and at reel 1553 (Bodleian Library, part 2 only).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paris (France) --  History --  Siege, 1590 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19008:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19008:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COPPIE OF A LETTER SENT IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England by a Gentleman, from the towne of Saint De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis in France.</p>
            <p>Wherein is truely ſet forth the good ſucceſſe of the Kings Maieſties forces againſt the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers and the Prince of Parmas power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the taking of a Conuoie of Victuals ſent by the Enemie to ſuccour Paris. And the grieuous eſtate of the ſaid Citie at this preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Scarlet for Thomas Nelſon. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19008:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19008:2"/>
            <head>THE COPPIE OF A Letter ſent into England by a Gentleman from the Towne of Saint Denis in France. Wherein is truely ſet forth the good ſucceſſe of the <hi>Kings Maieſties</hi> forces againſt the Leaguers and the <hi>Prince of Parmas</hi> power. With the taking of a Conuoy of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictuals ſent by the enemie to ſuccour <hi>Paris:</hi> And the grieuous eſtate of the ſaid Citie at this preſent.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the Prince of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma was come into the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of France, he ſought opportunitie where he might beſt plant himſelfe and his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in ſafetie, meaning by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie firſt to ſettle himſelfe in ſome part of the Kings regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to come with ſuch force as vppon ſodaine the king could not remoue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he ſhould raiſe his ſiege from before Paris, and then to make warre vpon him, which were greatly to the kinges hinderance, and the great aduantage of the enemie, for while the king had bin making warre vpon him, the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers might haue had the eaſier means to haue brought in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19008:3"/> freſh men and victuall to haue comforted that Citie, which is in wonderfull diſtreſſe, and the famine ſo grieuous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, as it was neuer greater at the ſiege of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. The true eſtate whereof is in moſt lamentable ſorte diſcourſed in the latter end of this Letter. But the king whoſe magnanimitie is knowen and founde ſufficient throughout the kingdome of France, perceiuing the intent and policie of the prince of Parma, neither meant to rayſe his ſiege from the Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> nor to ſuffer that parte of <hi>Picardie</hi> to be vnfurniſhed for the princes welcome. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing planted that notable warriour <hi>Monſieur de la Nowe,</hi> his principall lieftenant for thoſe partes, being a man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to be both politike and wiſe, and for martiall affaires found and approued to be one of the beſt in al France. This <hi>Monſieur de la Now</hi> hearing of the princes policie, who came thether with xx. thouſande men, diuided them into thrée parts, and purpoſed that one part ſhould goe vnto the towne of <hi>Lanie,</hi> being in number thrée thouſand, other fiue thouſand ſhould depart another waie for the ſuccour of the Leaguers, and to enlarge the armie of the Duke <hi>de Maine.</hi> The reſt he determined ſhould ſtaie with his owne perſon, whom he ſéemed at the firſt to conduct backe again towards Bruſſels, but on a ſodaine tooke another waie, and paſſed with his power towards Artoyes, where with great policie he is planted, yet far inough for doing any great harm, for he is ten leagues from the king, and hath intrenched him ſelfe within a wood, where he lieth verie ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Thus hauing diſpearced his armie into thrée partes, he appointed men of great experience to be leaders of them, ſo that <hi>Monſieur la Now</hi> aduiſed againſt whether of the armies hee were to ioyne his forces, ſo he caſt about &amp; met with the fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand who were marching to ioyne with the forces of <hi>du Maine,</hi> and thereby to make him and the Leaguers more ſtronger, againſt whom he had ſuch good ſucceſſe, that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited the greater part who eſcaped by flight, but many of them came ſhort home. And while <hi>la Now</hi> and his forces
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19008:3"/> were thus buſied, the other thrée thouſand went to a towne called <hi>Lanie,</hi> where making ſome ſhew of battel, the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof (as it is ſayd) had before ſolde it to the prince, and ſodainly he yéelded it, wherupon the ſoldiers who were Spaniards iſſued in and moſt cruelly put the inhabitants thereof to the ſword, and for certaintie thoſe butcherly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours and ſouldiers not therewith ſatiſfied, did cut and mangle the dead carcaſes into péeces. Which when it came to the eares of the king, he was verie ſorrowfull, &amp; wrote vnto his gouernour and forces in thoſe parts, commanding them to reuenge that bloudie act, wherein they ouerſlipped no fit occaſion for performing of the kings commandement. So that within few daies, notwithſtanding that they had ſtrongly entrenched themſelues, &amp; ſeated a ſufficient garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therein, with the loſſe of a few men the ſaid towne was recouered, and thoſe in the towne together with the ſaid ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers recompenced with the like rigour. Which doubtleſſe was but the iuſt iudgement of God vppon them, yea, the Captaine who at the firſt had betraied the ſayde towne and ſolde it for a péece of monie, was at the receit of the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſtabbed in with a dagger by a common ſouldier, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them reuelled away his Spaniſh reals, which he was receiuing for his reward, euen as wickedly as he had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the ſame. Thus may we ſée how the iuſt iudgement of God lighteth vpon ſuch wicked bloud ſuckers, &amp; although they are a ſmall time preſerued from it, yet in the ende it lighteth on their owne heads to their vtter confuſion. The prince of <hi>Parma</hi> hauing thus ſetled himſelfe and diuided his forces, he prepared to ſend a Conuoie of victuall to relieue the Citie of <hi>Paris:</hi> There were furniſhed for this Conuoie fiue hundreth wagons laden with victuals, namely béefe (a meate little vſed among the French) with mutton, and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie ſortes of fiſh both ſalt and freſh, with meale and corne vnground. There was alſo in the ſame twentie hundreth duſſen of bread all readie baked, becauſe of the great want of thoſe in the Citie, who were in ſuch caſe as they woulde
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19008:4"/> willingly haue eaten the ſame rawe, and the meale &amp; corne vnbaked, rather than they would haue ſtaid the dreſſing or baking thereof, ſo grieuous and extreame is their preſent famine, as after more at large appeareth. The kings maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hauing intelligence by his eſpials of this Conuoie, and that ſuch prouiſion was comming from the prince towards <hi>Paris,</hi> he determined with al policie and force to preuent the ſame, leaſt the rebellious Cities ſhoulde take courage vnto them, and thereby conceiue to haue ſome great reſiſtance by meanes of the enemies to the eſtate roiall, and ſo take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to triumph the more. This conuoie of victual, as I ſaid before, being ſent towardes <hi>Paris,</hi> came peaceably within foure or fiue leagues of the place, being garded with a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient band of men, whereof the king hauing not onely intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, but alſo of a Captaine which iſſued forth of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Paris,</hi> who with fiftéene hundred men went to méete and receiue the ſaid Conuoie of victuals, ſent forth preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diuerſe of his companies vnder the conduct of the Earle <hi>Chaſtilion,</hi> who practiſed not onely to intercept their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, but alſo their returning back againe, in which ſeruice the kings faithfull ſubiects ſo couragiouſly behaued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that in ſhort time they had their deſire, for on a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine being in a readines, they had a ſight of the ſaid wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons whom in ſhort ſpace they tooke, and ſlew all thoſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that came with the ſaid Conuoie to defend the ſame, &amp; made ſo hot an aſſault vpon the ſouldiers which iſſued ſorth of <hi>Paris,</hi> that they were al taken and ſlain with the loſſe of a few of the kings ſouldiers. The princes forces vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by their ſcoutes what had happened, durſt not come on nor approch to reſiſt the kings forces, while they were in fight with the Conuoie, whereof the valiant <hi>Chaſtilion</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing intelligence, venturouſlie ſet forward, and with the kings forces made towards them, and after a fierce and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant aſſalt made by them vpon the enemie, who at the firſt gaue a verie ſtrong and ſtout reſiſtance, they were all put to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, ſauing ſome few who eſcaped by flight, but neuer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19008:4"/> a man of thoſe eſcaped aliue which iſſued forth of the Citie of Paris.</p>
            <p>Thus with great ioy the ſaid Conuoie was brought into the ſaid towne of Saint Denis, the value whereof is by common eſtimation thirty thouſand pounds and better, being ſo much victuall as they could in reaſonable ſort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for them in thrée moneths.</p>
            <p>But ſo ſoone as the Pariſians heard of this newes, they were wonderous ſorrowfull, and were filled with ſo great heuines, that they reſted out of all hope to liue to ſée the day when any ſuccour can be ſent them by the enemy: and are at this preſent perſuaded, that all that euer the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> can do for their reliefe, is but to linger in that place where he is, and ſo to weary the king by detracting of time as he did in the low Countries, when he came thither firſt.</p>
            <p>Since this diſcomforture of the enemy, the Dutches of <hi>Guize,</hi> the Dutches of <hi>Maine, Le Cheuallier de Aumale,</hi> and diuers other of the chiefe of the Leaguers haue diſguiſed themſelues in ſimple attire and therby ſecretly iſſued forth of the ſaid Citie: by meanes wherof they are ſecretly eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, being not able any longer to endure the vnſpeakeable famine that is in the ſame: for the Launce-knightes euen againſt nature and reaſon are through the extreme famine conſtrained to eate their owne naturall children.</p>
            <p>Before this Conuoy aforeſaid, came downe towardes Parris, the prince of Parma after he had intrenched him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this wood, in the middle whereof is a ſtrong Caſtle, he ſent fiue hundreth of his horſemen to take view of the kings Camp: who were eſpied by two hundreth of the kings horſemen, thoſe two hundreth ſet vpon them and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them into their owne Trenches, where within their own Trenches and in the way to the Trenches they were all ſlaine.</p>
            <p>The prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> will not by any meanes enter into battell with the king, although hée haue béen verie much vrged therunto, yea, he hath endured the termes of cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19008:5"/> for his often denialls, hauing had much aduantage of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him to enter the field, wherein he excuſeth himſelfe in this ſort, that he hath no commiſſion from the king his maiſter, either to make battel or to fight in the field againſt the French king: and that his only charge was to vittaile <hi>Parris</hi> if he could, and to ſuccour thoſe of the League with his Forces and Councell. And with this reſolution, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth ſtill in the ſaid place, without offer of any fight, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome ſmall ſkirmiſhes betwéene his and the kinges Souldiers.</p>
            <p>It could not but be a great comfort vnto the people in their miſerie, when the king receiued ſome of them with great curteſie and gaue them foode, which droue the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nobillitie openly to confeſſe, and from their heartes to think, that he was a king of wonderfull vertuous and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull diſpoſition, and wold gladly haue yéelded themſelues, if their repentance might any way haue pacified the kings diſpleaſure, but for as much as they did all know, that the king who is and euer hath béen a true fulfiller of his word and promiſe, hath made an othe, that none of the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the deceaſed kings death ſhall eſcape and remaine pardonable, but that he will be reuenged of them for their vnnaturall treaſon, and that nothing but their liues ſhall pacifie their hainous murther committed: and in reſpect thereof, they kéepe themſelues ſo long as they may out of the kinges handes. The French king God be thanked, is wondrous well prouided of all thinges fit for warre, and with him is ioyned all the chiefeſt nobilitie and princes of France: hée hath of footemen thirtie thouſand, and ſeuen thouſand Horſſe. And with this Army the king continueth ſtill againſt <hi>Parris,</hi> which Citie is not likely to hold out long, eſpecially by reaſon ſome of the chiefe of the leaguers is fled from thence, whoſe countenance daily held them in awe. The Lord God bleſſe and proſper the kinges royall Maieſtie, and ſend him the victorie ouer all his enemies, to the glorie of God and aduancement of his holy word, for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19008:5"/> there was neuer in France a king of ſo noble a courage, ſo ſkilfull in the warres, and ſo hardie againſt the proudeſt foe, which is all the gréefe the enemies haue, becauſe they haue to deale againſt ſo valiant a Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Saint Denis <date>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of September. 1590.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:19008:6"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19008:6"/>
            <head>A TREATISE CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING THE EXTREME FAMINE OF THE CITIE of Paris at this preſent: which is as grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous as it was at the ſiege of Ieruſalem.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings Maieſtie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing often heard of the great famine and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable calamitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into the obſtinate pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians had wilfully plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelues, onely through the perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the chéefeſt of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers ſide, being for the moſt prat of the Cleargy. And albeit the extremitie were great, where into they were fallen, yet the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the increaſed miſery, ſince that time hath ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo lamentable in his royall cares, and amongſt all the reſt of his princely and honorable traine, that the remembrance thereof will not eaſily paſſe or bée raced out of minde: the certaine truth whereof, is as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19008:7"/>
            <p>After the king had entred S. <hi>Denis,</hi> as you heard long ſince with all his power, and that he was in full poſſeſſion thereof,<note place="margin">The Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of Paris iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed foorth to the king.</note> there iſſued out of <hi>Parris</hi> diuers and ſundry times many poore creatures, reſembling ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Anotamies of death, then people poſſeſſed with life, ſo ſore were they waſted with famine, and conſumed through extreame hunger, that excepting the ſkinne, there was nothing left to couer their fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bones. So that it preuailed nothing to be yoong or bewtifull in this caſe, or to boaſt of health, or to haue heapes of gold, for their ſtomackes deſired that, which for golde nor ſiluer could bee gotten, yea their verie harts failed them for want of neceſſary nouriſhment, wherupon they became careleſſe of life, deſiring death or ſpéedie deliuerie from this their miſerable eſtate, that they might no longer behold with their eyes, nor heare with their eares, the bitter cries of their ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued children, and the wonderfull multitudes of their friends and kindred, which for want of food daily died within that populous and great Citie. Reſolued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to finiſh their dolefull dayes, or to finde reliefe for maintenance of their loathed liues, with leaue of the cruell gouernours they iſſued (as I ſaid before) out of the Citie, and preſenting them ſelues before the kings ſouldiers, fel downe at their féet, yéelding them ſelues to the kings mercy, about the number of a ſcore at a time, men, women and children, who being brought incontinent before his roial maieſtie, ſo ſoone as they entered his ſight, with bitter teares trickling downe their chéekes they proſtrated themſelues at his féete, and as loude as their féeble voices woulde ſerue, they cried, <hi>Viue le Roy,</hi> God ſaue the king. His maieſtie amazed at the view of ſo pittifull a ſpectacle,<note place="margin">The kings mercifull heart.</note> and moued with a kingly compaſſion towards them, ſawe with his eies and conceiued in his heart, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19008:7"/> intollerable famiſhment the obſtinate Citie had alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die endured, but hauing a deſire to learne further of the ſtate thereof, after he had wel viewed the perſons of theſe miſerable men, he demanded of them the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of their comming. Wherevppon they returned this anſwere, that foraſmuch as they were not able anie longer to indure the grieuous famine wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they were brought by the long and deſerued ſiege which his Maieſtie mainteined about their City, and being brought ſo low, that the gouernours could not by reaſon of their weaknes imploie them in any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, they had frée liberty to depart the Citie if ſo they thought it conuenient: as being people that were like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly with many more in the Citie, to cauſe an infection to ariſe by means of ſicknes among the reſt of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, wherefore, ſayd they, moſt noble and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious king, wee are come vnto your Highnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that wee are vnworthie of anie longer life, by reaſon we haue bin moſt vniuſt and rebellious ſubiects,<note place="margin">The Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s kept by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint.</note> and vnworthie that ſo gracious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a prince ſhould open his mouth vnto vs, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, moſt mighty king, had it not bin through wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſwaſions, we had neuer yéelded to holde on ſo curſed a ſide, but with whome perſwaſions could not preuaile, they vſed meanes to inforce, being well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that they holde the moſt parte by conſtraint, whoſe bodies being encloſed within the ſtonie walls of <hi>Paris,</hi> haue euerie daie their heartes infolded with their king, conſidering within what ſmall compas there is foode inough with fauour and gentlenes to be gotten, and yet they be at the point of death euen for a ſmall quantitie of bread, that may with their eyes beholde euen plentie among beaſts while they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues pine and cannot come by it, whereby the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is ſhewed betwixt the fauour and furie of a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19008:8"/> king, and therewithall, the recompence of obedience and rebellion:</p>
            <p>We confeſſe therefore, moſt noble king, that th mightie and iuſt God hath bent himſelfe againſt vs and poured foorth the violl of his wrath ouer theſe traiterous confederates of the Leagures, of which number we muſt of force account and acknowledge we haue too long béene, and therefore we humblie ſubmit our ſelues into your maieſties hands, to deale with vs as it ſéemeth good in your ſight.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie hauing heard this lamentable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, reuiued their hearts with a fauourable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and according to his princely diſpoſition, in a milde manner demaunded what prouiſion of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals (in their iudgements) remayned yet in the citie, and what it was wherewith they hoped to ſuſtayne the liues of ſo infinite a multitude as remayned in the towne, wiſhing to declare the ſame in all trueth and ſimplicitie of heart, euen as they would hope to finde mercie at his handes for their knowen and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt rebellion, and how long time they ſuppoſed the ſame would laſt.</p>
            <p>Before the mightie and dreadfull God of heauen, who knowes the ſecrets of the harts, and ſhall iudge the thoughts that are hatched by vntruth, ſo wil we, ſaid they, ſhew and declare this to the king, as farre as our memorie and knowledge doth ſtretch. And if your maieſtie find vs falſe let the ſame be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with the vildeſt death that euer anie did endure. And herewithall one of them who was knowne of beſt iudgement, and that had béen of great account in times paſt, put forth his voice before the king, and moſt part of the princes and nobles about him,<note place="margin">Neceſsitie findes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhiftes.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as followeth.</p>
            <p>Neceſſitie the whetſtone of mans wit, hauing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19008:8"/> me among theſe my companions and ſorrowful aſſociates, with an infinite multitude of my friendes, kinſfolke and neighbours to ſearch for ſuſtenance, for the maintenance of me and my poore wife and children,<note place="margin">Neceſsity finds many ſhiftes.</note> inquired by all meanes after foode when it became ſcant in the Citie, being the onely care that euery perſon had to ſéeke for the ſame: and albeit after a ſmall time that we were beſéeged, wholeſome foode was kept wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cloſe and ſcant among vs, yet our eares were euer ſo diligent to hearken after it, that by one meanes or other we alwaies heard where it was to bee had for money, and although the prouiſion was great within the citie, yet by reaſon of the marueilous multitude of inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, within fiue monethes after, there was no whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome foode to be had for gold nor treaſure, for the Nobles and principall of the citie, ſuſpecting a long ſéege, got as much thereof as they could for their owne prouiſion, and the cloyſters with the vniuerſitie did the like: and as for the Clargie, they ſtayed not behinde any in that matter, being men wiſe enough to take the choice before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which meanes the common ſorte of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſoone found the ſmart thereof, and in vaine ſought they after that they could not finde: when fleſh failed, butter and chéeſe began to grow precious at rich mens tables, though at the firſt they much repined thereat, as people that had not béene much acquainted with ſuch courſe cates. But the iuſt God ſéeing our vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hartes, that ſcorned his gifts, and deſpiſed his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, in two monethes after ſent ſuch a change,<note place="margin">Rats, mice &amp; other vermine good meate in Paris.</note> that the fleſh of Horſes, Aſſes, Dogges, Cats, Rats, Mice, Weaſels, and Moles, became daintie diſhes at gentle mens tables, and bore ſuch a price, that no poore perſon was able to compas any, &amp; then our queaſie ſtomacks began to be contented with any thing, were it a frying panne full of Frogs, a diſh of ſnailes,, or a Skellet full of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19008:9"/> garden wormes ſod in broth: ſhe that went in her hoode, would haue béene glad to haue licked her lippes after them, and would haue bidden her deareſt friend to the banquete, had hee not béene of her owne houſhold, ſo ſwéete a ſauce and ſo ſauory did hunger make the ſame to taſte, and yet many of thoſe that thus haue fled, and yet woulde bee glad to méete with the worſt of theſe thinges rehearſed before they felt the force of hunger, with many othes, ſaid they would ſtarue vnto death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſuch corrupt thing ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort their ſtomacks, and yet was all this but a taſte of famine, and nothing comparable to that which afterwarde fell vpon vs, for in ſhort time our breade of peaſe, tares, oates and acorns vtterly failed vs, ſo that none could be had or found in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place to be ſolde, although we would haue killed one another with thruſt, to haue gotten the quantitie of a farthing loafe (farre worſe then any which in former time we gaue our horſes) though we would haue giuen a French crowne for ſo much, and thoſe vermine alſo that we prepared and dreſſed, as before is ſhewed, was on all ſides ſo caught vp and eaten, that in the end there was none to be gotten, neither for one nor other: and then began ſuch mortalitie through famine,<note place="margin">Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand dead of famine in Paris.</note> that ten thouſand haue already dyed thereof, as may be ſéene in the regiſter booke, and at this preſent, ten thouſand more are like to periſh through the like extremitie. A moſt grieuous and intollerable burden ſufficient to inforce a flinty hart to remorſe and pittie, how great a warning ought this to be to all cities that are in a flouriſhing eſtate, where plentie poureth forth her treaſures, in ſo much that delicacie is become lothſome, in reſpect of an vnſatiable deſire, and daintineſſe will not be contented without great ſuperfluitie, euery man wiſhes for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and no man thinketh that he hath goodes enough, and few remaine thankfull for any thing: conſider, you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19008:9"/> that vſe exceſſe, and wil not ſo much as lift vp your eyes, much leſſe your hartes, to render praiſes for ſo great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, conſider (I ſay) how ioyful &amp; glad many nobles &amp; men of great worſhip would be of the worſt bit or bone that you fling vnder the table to your dogs, while your ſelues in the middeſt of your exceſſe, ſit turning with your kniues point, the meate in diuers diſhes, and can ſcant among them all finde one morſell to fit your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, notwithſtanding how gladſom a preſent the leaſt of your loaues would be in Paris, let thoſe imagine that can conceiue of their miſerie, and how many woulde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate vpon their knées, to be preferred, as it were, to the ſhaking of the table cloth, or carrying away of the tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. Vndoubtedly, I am perſwaded, that if the dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt mouthed dame in Europe had but one monethes experience of the like want, ſhe ſhould afterwarde while ſhe did liue, eſtéeme better of the leaſt crumme, then ſhe doth now of all the dainties vpon the table. I beſéech God be mercifull vnto vs, &amp; forgiue our vnthankfulnes, &amp; grant vs grace to reforme our liues, leſt we be plagued for our leudnes. But to returne to the former matter.</p>
            <p>The King hauing heard this doulefull diſcourſe, procéeded further,<note place="margin">The kings ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund.</note> and demaunded whether before their iſſuing forth of the Citie, they had found no meanes whereby they of the towne might haue ſomething to put into their bellies to ſtrengthen the hart, and to helpe the ſtomacke, and abate the fury of hunger.</p>
            <p>Thrée wéekes (ſaide the reporter) wee continued without any ſuſtenance, ſaue onely Flies and Béettles,<note place="margin">Flyes and Beetles.</note> whereby we ſought to ſuſtaine our ſelues, with diuers other like thinges, till in the end our emptie intrels en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced vs to ſéeke ſome meanes for reliefe, at what time the people deuiſed to gather all kinde of rootes ſuch as grew within the compaſſe of the walles, which being partched or otherwiſe dryed, we ground them in a mill,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19008:10"/> and therewith made vs breade, but alas, ſlender comfort conceaued wee thereby, though we were glad of any thing, for in leſſe then two dayes, our people were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to finde ſome other remedie againſt hunger, whereupon it was deuiſed to ſaw all the timber wee coulde come by and conuert it into duſt,<note place="margin">Bread of ſaw-duſt.</note> and thereof to make vs another ſorte of breade, which deuice continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed longer then many of the former, and contented vs a great deale better, by reaſon we had ſome quantitie thereof to fill our emptie ſtomackes, but this was not to be had without money, except a body had of their owne wherewith to make it, in ſo much that all the wood plankes and bordes which conueniently we coulde come by, was put to that vſe, and when this began to grow ſomething ſcant, euery man hauing care principally to nouriſh himſelfe and meditating dayly how to inuent meanes to procure ſuſtenance, being a thing wherein euery one applyed his wits, at length the extremitie was ſuch, that the Churchyardes were digged for deade mens bones, and all the ſaide bones they carryed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into one place in the citie,<note place="margin">Dead mens bones eaten</note> where they might lye from the raine, the which afterwarde being waſhed and dryed, were beaten in péeces and ground, and thereof an other ſorte of bread was made, and thus we were glad to féed our ſtomackes with the bones of the dead. In which time if it may pleaſe your Maieſtie to pardon my long and tedious diſcourſe, I am to declare a moſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full accident which then happened.<note place="margin">Men worth twenty or thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There was then dwelling among vs, a very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ſubſtantiall man, which was Sargeant ouer one of our companies, for the ſkill they founde to bee in him, who was imployed as were the reſt of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to be a ſouldier in the Citie for thoſe which of late were eſtéemed men worth twentie or thirtie thouſand pounde, were enforced to become common ſouldiers,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19008:10"/> whoſe ſubſtance thereby is waſted and brought to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſo much néede haue they of men in the citie. This Sargeant before ſpoken of, comming home to his houſe about ſeuen dayes agoe, his wife and his children came preſently running about him, hoping hee had brought ſomething for them to eate, at what time there was a neighbour or two in the houſe ſtaying his comming, and with his wife lamenting the common calamitie, hoping from his mouth to heare ſome newes of the yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of the Citie into your highneſſe handes. But the cryes of the ſtarued children interrupting the talke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and his neighbours, the poore man with a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull hart ſat him downe, fetching a déepe ſigh, not knowing what to doe for them, the children ſtill cloying his eares with their pittifull complaintes. Ha Father, ſaide they, will you ſée vs dye for want of bread? if there remained any thing vpon our bones beſide the ſkinne,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of children for lacke of food.</note> we would not let to féede thereon: but if no other reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die may be founde, let the one of vs ſerue for foode to the other, or els ſpare not our liues to féede our mother and you, better were it for vs by death to be ridde of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, then to endure a famine the ende whereof is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne: is there ought in this Citie ſaue men to féede vpon? why may not the one of vs deuoure the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, or why are the deade bodies of men couered in the ground that might ſerue a hungry ſtomacke to féede vpon. The father looking vpon them with a heauie hart, after many teares ſhed on euery ſide, hauing pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered theſe ſpéeches, ſtarted vp as a man purpoſed to giue them encouragement, and with a comfortable voice briefly ſaide vnto them, be content my children, and be of good cheare, ſo ſoone as theſe my friends are gone, I will giue you that which ſhall content you, but alas, if it were ſufficient for vs all, I would be loth to part with their company, notwithſtanding I hope they conſider
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19008:11"/> the time as it is, and will not thinke any diſcourteſie herein, being aſſured, themſelues in the like caſe woulde doe the like to me, then turning to his neighbours hee ſaide, the time hath béene we would not haue denied our meate, but our money, but now our money is nothing in reſpect of our meat, and woe be vnto them that would not giue the poore money to buye meate where it is to be had, wherefore I beſeech you leaue vs a while till we haue refreſhed our ſelues, then after I will anſwere any thing I ſhall heare ſpoken by you: hereupon the two men departed, and ſhortly after, knowing that their din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner laſted not long, theſe perſons went againe thether, knocking and calling for him, maruelling that no body came to make anſwere, wherefore being very familiar friendes, and ſuſpecting they had beene in their vpper chamber, went vp, whereinto they no ſooner entered, but preſently they eſpyed the good man,<note place="margin">A man firſt hanged his wife &amp; children, and after him ſelfe for lacke of food.</note> his wife and two children (about the age of fourteene yeares) all han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged one beſide another, and a bill vpon the good mans breſt, wherein was writen, <hi>By this meanes did I firſt ſet my wife and children out of miſerie, and after my ſelfe, for which offence I aske the Lorde mercy and forgiueneſſe:</hi> and that your highneſſe may be the better ſatiſfied of the truth hereof, the men be here that firſt heard his wordes, and after were wofull witneſſes of this Tragedy, in ſuch extremitie remaines this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Citie.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie that ſcant could refraine teares to heare this dolefull diſcourſe,<note place="margin">The Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of their owne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note> anſwered: Ah Paris, thy bloud be on thy owne heade, it is thy ſelfe and not I that hath cauſed this great calamitie, the Lord be witneſſe twixt thee and me, and rewarde me after the innocencie of my hart? after theſe wordes cauſing the ſtarued people to be refreſhed, he departed into his chamber, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that no more ſhould be ſuffered to come forth of the Citie in ſuch ſorte.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19008:11"/>
            <p>Thus haue you hard the good ſucceſſe of the Kinges Maieſtie, whom no doubt, Almightie God proſpereth and preſerueth, with the euill ſucceſſe of rebellious people, and the enimies againſt Gods truth, whom hee in iuſtice puniſheth, and doth in his iuſt iudgements bring to confuſion: Almightie God ſtil proſper the kings procéedings, and ſend confuſion to his enimies, except they ſpéedely repent and yéelde themſelues vnto him, as in right they ought, which God graunt. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>FINIS.</hi>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of a walled garden or fortified town, as seen from above (?)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
